<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mendeley on Alex M. Chubaty</title>
    <link>/tags/mendeley/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mendeley on Alex M. Chubaty</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/mendeley/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>more on journal abbreviations in Mendeley</title>
      <link>/post/2013-06-20-more-on-journal-abbreviations-in-mendeley/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2013-06-20-more-on-journal-abbreviations-in-mendeley/</guid>
      <description>Wow, my other posts on the topic are getting a lot of hits!
Some exciting info for anyone still struggling with getting abbreviated journal names working with Mendeley: this feature is coming soon!
 This is currently on our roadmap for Mendeley Desktop 1.10. Expected release date is the start of August.
 From the mockups and descriptions the good folks at Mendeley have provided it looks like they&amp;rsquo;re doing a great job of addressing this shortcoming of their current product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>enabling Libre/OpenOffice plugin for Mendeley 1.5</title>
      <link>/post/2012-04-13-enabling-libreopenoffice-plugin-for-mendeley-1-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-04-13-enabling-libreopenoffice-plugin-for-mendeley-1-5/</guid>
      <description>I upgraded to using Mendeley v 1.5 (because previous versions don&amp;rsquo;t work on Ubuntu 12.04 Precise) and I had problems installing the OpenOffice plugin. Normally this is easy: in Mendeley you select the Tools menu and go to Install OpenOffice Plugin. However, for whatever reason the software can&amp;rsquo;t find the plugin, and I get this error:
Mendeley couldn&#39;t locate unopkg in the default location. It should be in the &#39;program&#39; subdirectory of the path where OpenOffice is installed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>list of abbreviated journal names</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-28-list-of-abbreviated-journal-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-02-28-list-of-abbreviated-journal-names/</guid>
      <description>As a followup to my previous post, I wrote a script to generate the master list of journal names and their abbreviations from Web of Science.
The script is designed to be used in conjunction with the previous one, and is also written in perl (which I&amp;rsquo;m still learning) and can be downloaded here or viewed here. Improvements and suggestions welcome.
At the bottom of the script is a list of my custom journal names and abbreviations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Easily make custom Mendeley citation styles</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-01-easily-make-custom-mendeley-citation-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-02-01-easily-make-custom-mendeley-citation-styles/</guid>
      <description>I came across this incredibly useful site today:
http://csleditor.quist.de/csleditor/show/1/example-citation-style
No longer need to manually edit custom citation style (CSL) files for Mendeley (and Zotero) within a text file!!!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Citation Styles in Mendeley</title>
      <link>/post/2011-11-07-custom-citation-styles-in-mendeley/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2011-11-07-custom-citation-styles-in-mendeley/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m an avid user of Mendeley citation management software (CMS), and am pleased with the capabilities of this cross-platform, open-source, and *free* referencing tool. However, one limitation I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered is that it does not have very many citiation styles preinstalled, and although many additional formats are available to download through the Mendeley interface, it does not (yet) provide a built-in style editor to customize citiation styles.
Fortunately, Mendeley uses Citation Style Language v1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>